<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The suffering condition of the servants of the Lord at this day vindicated and some reasons given why the people called Quakers do own the doctrine of Christ, to continue in it, and to meet together in the name and fear of the Lord, to wait upon him, and worship him in spirit and truth, not withstanding they meet with sufferings in this present time for so doing : Bristol, the 6th month, 1662 / John Audland.</title>
            <author>Audland, John, 1630-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22605</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12124898</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12124898</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54550</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26199)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54550)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 756:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The suffering condition of the servants of the Lord at this day vindicated and some reasons given why the people called Quakers do own the doctrine of Christ, to continue in it, and to meet together in the name and fear of the Lord, to wait upon him, and worship him in spirit and truth, not withstanding they meet with sufferings in this present time for so doing : Bristol, the 6th month, 1662 / John Audland.</title>
                  <author>Audland, John, 1630-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54550:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54550:1"/>
            <p>The Suffering Condition OF THE Servants of the Lord At this day, Vindicated: And ſome Reaſons given why the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> do own the Doctrine of Chriſt, to continue in it, and to meet together in the Name and Fear of the Lord, to wait upon him, and worſhip him in Spirit and Truth, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they meet with ſufferings in this preſent time for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Briſtol,</hi> the 6th. Month, 1662. <hi>JOHN AUDLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Hearken unto me, ye that knew righteouſneſs, the people in whoſe heart is my Law; fear ye not the reproach of men, neither be ye afraid of their revilings; for the Moth ſhall eat them up like a Garment, and the Worm ſhall eat them like Wool; but my righteouſneſs ſhall be for ever and my ſalvation from generation to generation,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 51.7, 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of God's Elect, it is God that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 8.33.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? Shall tribulation, or diſtreſs, or perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſs, or peril or ſword as it is written, For thy ſake we are killed all the day long, we are counted as ſheep for the ſlaughter) nay in all theſe things we are more than Conquerors, through him that loved us; for I am perſwaded, that neither Death, nor Life; nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 8.35, 36, 37, 38.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:54550:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54550:2"/>
            <head>The ſuffering condition of the Servants of the Lord at this day, vindicated, &amp;c:</head>
            <p>THe good and bleſſed Day of the Lord is come, and the Heavenly Viſitation of Life, wherein the Light of Righteouſneſs is ſpringing up unto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people, and many have received the bleſſed Viſitation of the Lord, and are made partakers of his Heavenly Power, by which they are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened and raiſed up unto newneſs of life, to ſerve him, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in truth and righteouſneſs; and the bleſſed day wherein the Lord viſited us, and the notable works which the Lord hath wrought, and his noble acts which he hath done, are not by us to be forgotten, but are recorded in our hearts, as things remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and conſiderable, to be remembred by us while we have a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the earth, and that with fear and reverence in our hearts unto the Lord our God, who is great and mighty, whom we have known to execute Judgement in righteouſneſs, to the judging and bringing down of that which was once exalted; for when the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Year of the Lord came unto us, Judgement was laid to the Line, and the Lord did ariſe to ſhake terribly the Earth, the loftineſs of man was bowed down, and the haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of man was laid low, that the Lord alone might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted; and the Earth reeled to and fro, and was removed like a Shepherd's Tent, and the Light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was as a fire, and the holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> One as a flame, to burn up the thorns and the thickets in a day; many faces gathered paleneſs, and hearts grew weak, and knees feeble, and many had their hands upon their loins, becauſe of the great travel that was upon them, becauſe of the mighty Power of the Lord which was made manifeſt in them, for the bringing down of that which had been exalted againſt him, and for the reſtoration of the oppreſſed Captive, that deliverance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54550:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>be known from the power of Satan, and from the bondage of corruption, that we being ſet free wherein we were held, might ſerve the Lord in truth and ſingleneſs of heart, and wait upon him, and follow the leadings of his Spirit, in the exerciſe of our hearts and minds in ſerving and worſhipping the Lord our God; And ſo the God of Heaven hath revealed and made manifeſt the way of Life and Peace, the way wherein comfort and ſatisfaction to the ſoul is found, the Gate of Mercy, even the entrance to the everlaſting Kingdom of Reſt and Joy for evermore; which although it be ſtrait and narrow, and a croſs to the fleſhly part, and earthly ground and wiſdom, yet it is eaſie, pleaſant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful living in the Spirit, and becoming little, even as a Child, for ſo muſt he become that enters in at the ſtrait Gate, to eat of the Tree of Life which is in the midſt of the Paradice of God: So we have found the way of everlaſting peace, (through the rich mercy, and tender viſitation of the Lord) walking in the Spirit, and living in that which mortifies the deeds of the fleſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubject to the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Here is reſt to the ſoul; here is the ſweet viſitations of the Lord known, which are as the former and latter rain, to refreſh the lowly in heart, and poor in ſpirit: Here waiting upon the Lord, the ſtrength is renewed, and here the Lord ſpeaks peace to people, even as they are in Chriſt the Power of God, growing up in him, who is the truth and the life, they are poſſeſſors of laſting peace which God ſpeaks not to the wicked) which is the portion of the upright in heart; and as the Lord hath made manifeſt the way of peace, life and everlaſting happineſs, he hath alſo diſcovered the contrary, even the way of miſery, darkneſs and deſtruction, the way which is broad, and many in the luſts of the fleſh takes pleaſure in it, following the motions of the fleſh, and the deſires of the carnal mind, reſiſting the motions of Gods good Spirit, and hating the bleſſed Light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo ſpends away their precious time, and in this ſtate, that is to ſay in the fleſh, reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit of the Lord, they cannot ſerve God, nor pleaſe him, nor worſhip him in truth, though they may profeſſe him in words, and draw near him with their mouth; yet being in the fleſh contrary to the Spirit of Truth, the ear turned away from hearing of God's Law, their prayers are abomination, their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54550:3"/>plowing is ſin, their ſacrifice is as <hi>Cains,</hi> not accepted by the Lord, no peace from God, no true reſt, no ſatisfaction, no behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the countenance of the Lord, nor no aſſurance of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Inheritance which never fades away, but an earneſt of wrath, pain, miſery, anguiſh and trouble, which will come upon all who live and dye in diſobedience of the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And ſo we ſee the Way of Life to all that believe in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and the way of death to all who live in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and are not changed by the power of God, and tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from death to life, and from the Kingdom of darkneſs, into the Kingdom of the dear Son of God.</p>
            <p>And theſe things are of great concernment unto us, and we ſee it is very needful to wait upon the Lord, and to follow the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Spirit, that we may feel his power to preſerve us in his will, out of the evil of the World, that ſo in the power of the Lord our God we may war a good Warfare, and finiſh our courſe with joy.</p>
            <p>And verily this is a matter of great weight unto us, even to have our hearts exerciſed towards the Lord in obedience to his Will, in what he requireth of us, that we may have a Conſcience void of offence towards him: And ſo the day of the Lord God being come, and his Eternal Power made known in many hearts, by which many are raiſed to ſerve him, and obey him, yea to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him according to his own Will, and the leadings of his good Spirit; We are even conſtrained by the Power of the Lord to meet together in his Name and Fear, to wait upon him, and to worſhip him, and alſo to exhort one another in his holy Power, as the Spirit of the Lord directs; yea, and ſo much the more as the day appeareth: And this we find alſo to be according to the Scriptures of Truth, and practice of the Servants of the Lord in former dayes, who did not forſake the aſſmebling of themſelves together, but met often, and ſometime in one place, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in another, as they were directed in the fear of the Lord: <hi>And they that feared the Lord ſpake often one unto another, and the Lord hearkened and heard it, and a Book of Remembrance was written for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his Name: And they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54550:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall be mine ſaith the Lord, in the day that I make up my Jewels, and I will ſpare them as a man ſpareth his own Son that ſerveth him:</hi> And this was in a time when the proud were called happy, and they that wrought wickedneſs were ſet up, and they that tempted God were delivered; yet even in ſuch a time did they that feared the Lord ſpeak often together, and alſo in the time when the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt was publiſhed by the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, many were brought into the obedience of the truth, and were gathered from the <hi>Jews</hi> Worſhip and way of ſervice, [and they, to wit the <hi>Jews,</hi> could plead more iuſtly for the Antiquity of their way of Worſhip, and their order in their Worſhip, than many who this day profeſs themſelves to be Chriſtians, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church] and in that time did they meet together, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in a Chamber, ſometime in an houſe, and ſometime in an upper room, as the Lord directed them, and as they had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities; and gathered Churches which met at Houſes, and waited upon the Lord, and exhorted one another, and might all ſpeak one by one, as the Spirit of the Lord lead them, that all might hear, and all be comforted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And we do not read that the</hi> Jews <hi>made a Law, (or the</hi> Romans <hi>ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who at that time had the Principality) that they ſhould not meet above four together, or if they met five, or above, they ſhould be fined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed the <hi>Jews</hi> who believed not, were bad enough, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Saints from City, and halled out of Houſes they that profeſſed the Name of Jeſus, and ſometime ſcourged them; but they are evil examples to be followed, and it's pitty that any who profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, ſhould do the like to any that meet together in the fear of the Lord, to ſerve him, and walk peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in godlineſs and fear.</p>
            <p>And why may not more than four meet together lawfully to worſhip God, in the account of God and all juſt men? Why may not ten? Yea and why may not a bundred and more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Provided ſtill it be to worſhip God, and ſerve him. And why may not alſo ſome come in amongſt them who are unbelievers, that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the way of truth, that they may come to hear, and learn, and be convinced of all, and go away, and confeſs that God is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54550:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>there of a truth; and if there be more that come upon the ſame account, it is alſo approved.</p>
            <p>Sure that was a great concourſe of people, when the Diſciples were met in one place, where three thouſand were pricked to the heart at one time. Had it been juſtifiable in the <hi>Jews</hi> at that time to hinder ſuch gatherings of people together, or ſuch Speakers as were, who ſpake as the Spirit of the Lord gave them utterance? The Jews were very angry with them, and commanded them to ſpeak no more in the Name of Jeſus; but they obeyed God rather than man, and ſpoke boldly the Word of the Lord, and the Lord was with them, yea and filled their hearts with joy and comfort, though ſometime they were put in the Stocks, and ſometime in Priſon.</p>
            <p>So we do verily find both by the Teſtimony of the Spirit of God in our hearts, and alſo by the Teſtimony of the Scriptures, That our meeting together to worſhip the Lord, and to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, is according to the mind of God, and alſo to the practiſe of the Saints in former dayes; and although we be of the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſide, as the Saints were in times paſt, yet we are content in the will of the Lord to give up unto him in all theſe things: And ſurely if they that cauſeth us to ſuffer, did but diligently mind and conſider their way and weapons which they go on in, and war with, they may find themſelves to be on the perſecuting ſide, and ſee the Saints did not ſo, neither war with ſuch weapons; for the Saints weapons were not carnal, but ſpiritual, and mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds; for 'tis the ſpiritual Weapons that can and doth conquer the man of ſin within, and can ſubdue every high thought and imagination, and bring under whatſoever is contrary to the Will of God: 'Tis the Eternal Word of the everlaſting God that is quick and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſharper than any two-edged ſword, which divides within, where no carnal Weapon can divide: And if any think we be not in the way of the Lord, let them come forth with ſpiritual Weapons, or with the beſt they have, laying aſide all carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, Club and Staffe, force and compulſion, for that will never overcome a ſpiritual Enemy; it may kill outwardly, but cannot kill ſpiritual wickedneſs; and coming forth with theſe Weapons,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54550:5"/>this is like men that profeſs Chriſtianity, and would be far more comely amongſt the ſober and honeſt-bearted people, and far more like to the Saints, then halling out of houſes by force with carnal weapons, and caſting into priſon for no other thing but owning the Doctrine of Chriſt, and meeting together to worſhip God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And then this be offered as the prevailing Argument; There is a Law made lately, that will not allow you; and if you do, we muſt fine you, or we muſt take your Goods, or commit you to priſon, or cauſe you to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit your Eſtates: Therefore we charge you give over, if not, we muſt proceed againſt you, and break your Meetings with carnal Weapons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! where is the ſpiritual Weapons, the power to convince gain-ſayers, Goſpel-Miniſters that went forth without Club or ſtaff; for ſay we, convince our Conſciences, or elſe we dare not do it; for we may not diſobey the Lord becauſe of theſe things?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Well, then</hi> (ſay they) <hi>you will be ruinated; have you no wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? will you ſpoile your ſelves with theſe things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> More is the pity, (ſay we) that we may not ſerve the Lord, and worſhip him; but ſuch lufferings will be exerciſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us by a people that profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones too: Well, ſay we, we muſt commit our cauſe to the Lord, and even give up all to him, who knows how to deliver on us by a people that profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones too: Well, ſay we, we muſt commit our cauſe to the Lord, and even give up all to him, who knows how to deliver the righteous out of all their trouble.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>I but</hi> (ſay they) <hi>cannot you meet four, and no more?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We ſay, We may not limit the Lord, neither in the things of God muſt we order our ſelves. And again, if ſome could ſtoop to that, it would not ſerve neither.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Then</hi> (ſay they) <hi>you muſt be forced, and then you, or ſome of you will yeild, and then we will boaſt over you with thoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54550:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But we ſay, that force with carnal Weapons, by pains and penalcies, as it was not the way of the Lord, nor the practiſe of the true Chriſtians, ſo neither doth it effect the end, for it will never make men truly religious, neither will it be for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the end to them that go about ſo to compel; no, nor yet any comfort in the mean time; for there is a <hi>Prick</hi> that meets with the Perſecutors now and then, which ſtops their furious driving, and gives them no eaſe in their Way; as it was vvith <hi>Saul</hi> while he perſecuted the Saints and brought them bound, both Men and Women, that believed in the Lord Jeſus; and he is not a good example in that to be followed; <hi>for he made havock of the Church, entering into every Houſe, and halling men and women, committing them to priſon, having Authority from the Chief-Prieſts, and being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly mad againſt them,</hi> (Acts 8 3. Acts 26.10, 11.) as he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards confeſſed; and as he vvent to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> with Authority and Commiſſion, he vvas ſtruck dovvn for all his Authority, and heard a voice ſaying to him, <hi>Why perſecuteſt thou me? it is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks.</hi> And it will be very hard for all ſuch vvho perſecute the Children of the Lord, the Lord will ſmite them one vvay or another; if they be not ſmitten to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: But if the Lord ſmite them often, and they ſtill go on to ſin more and more; he will eaſe him of his Adverſaries, and avenge him of his Enemies, and ſmite them vvith an irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtroke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> And if it be objected, <hi>That theſe were Jews that did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt, that thus perſecuted the Chriſtians, and it was evil done of them; but we are a Reformed Church, and we do it in zeal to Chriſt, that people might be all of one way, and the Law doth allow us to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 'Tis anſvvered thus: The <hi>Jews</hi> had a zeal for God which vvas not according to knovvledge; and they had a Law alſo, by which they judged the Holy One that he ought to dye; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſuppoſed they did God ſervice, and for the defending of the Law, yet indeed they fought againſt God, and they had as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54550:6"/>much to ſay for their vvay of Worſhip, it being ancient, and they vvhich differed from them, their vvay vvas but nevv in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance: I ſay, the <hi>Jews</hi> might plead for their Way far more groundedly, than many novv; eſpecially people vvho neither live in their Way of Worſhip, according to the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law, no nor yet according to the Saints in the Primitive times; And thoſe that profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, and yet perſecute the Innocent, they are far more guilty than the <hi>Jews</hi> vvere, inaſmuch as they both profeſs more Light, and alſo vvalk ſo quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their ovvn Profeſſion; yea and to the example of Chriſt, vvhom they profeſs (and the true Chriſtians) who ſaid, <hi>Love your Enemies, pray for them that perſecute you;</hi> not perſecute them that pray for you: Neither had the Saints ſuch Weapons to bring people into their Church, as is now uſed, but ſpiritual ones, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through God, and vvent forth in his Power; this brought peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be of one heart, and one vvay, and to ſerve the Lord with one mind, which force, vvith carnal Weapons, vvill never accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh, to bring people to be of one vvay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> And as it's ſaid, <hi>But ſome will yeild, and then we will rejoice in that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 'Tis anſwered, That's a bad Work to force people, and compel them to deny that vvhich God hath made manifeſt to them to be truth; and the greater is their ſin that ſo do. 'Tis ſaid, that <hi>Saul</hi> compelled ſome to blaſpheme againſt the Name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, when he raged ſo againſt them; but he afterward confeſſed it as a great ſin: And though ſome did ſo, or do ſo, yet that is no confirmation to the perſecutors, that they are in the Way of God; no, nor yet a true Teſtimony againſt the perſecuted, that they are not in the Way of God; neither doth it truly convert men at all: Indeed force and compulſion may make ſome men conform to that outwardly, vvhich otherwiſe they would not do; but that is nothing of weight, their hearts are never the better, but are rather worſe, and more hypocrites than before, for force doth but make Hypocrites at the moſt; for it is God alone by his powerful Word of Life operating in the hearts of people, that
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:54550:6"/>changeth them, and reneweth them in the Spirit of their minds, and brings them into the true Service and Worſhip, even to draw near him with their hearts, and to worſhip him in Spirit and Truth, and it's out of man's power, and that which God doth not require of men at this day, to force by penalties and carnal Weapons to this or that Worſhip, and is abſolutely againſt the practice of the Saints, and the Spirit of Jeſus, as alſo againſt Chriſt's Royal Law, which is, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, even ſo do ye unto them:</hi> Now let every man make it his own caſe, <hi>He ſaith his way is the way of God, and anothers is not:</hi> Well then, would he be forced to leave his own way, and to go to the other, vvhich he is not ſatisfied of to be according to the mind of God, eſpecially when nothing is offered to convince his Conſcience, or perſwade his mind and underſtanding, but force and compulſion: Surely no man would be ſo dealt with in his own caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But if it be ſaid, <hi>We have Power and a Law, and we are wiſe and learned men, and we would not be forced from our Religion, but we would force people to ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This hath no weight in it at all; for you ought to put your ſelves in the ſame capacities as them you deal with are; and to conſider your ſelves in their condition; they are as ſtrongly (it may be more) perſwaded in their Conſciences by the Spirit of God, that their Way is right, than you are of yours. Well then, (weighing theſe things) would you be forced? Would you have others to deal ſo with you, if you vvere in their condition, and they in yours? Let God's Witneſs anſwer in all Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſee if theſe vvays of forcing in matters of Conſcience to God-wards, be not quite contrary to the practice of the Saints, and to the Royal Law of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Beſides, though it be ſaid, <hi>But we judge we are in the right, and our way is the true way.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54550:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It's anſwered, You may be miſtaken, many hath, that have had thoughts their way was right; and while you have not the infallible Witneſs of God's Spirit with you, to teſtifie to your Way, peradventure you may err as the former Forcers have done; and then you cauſe people to ſin, if you could force them to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, and to deny, as <hi>Saul</hi> did; for if he that turneth a ſinner from the error of his vvay, (who hath erred from the Truth) doth ſave a ſoul, and hide a multitude of ſins, then they that force people from the Way of God, and cauſe them to err, doth bring ſouls into death, and ſo bring innocent blood upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yea the blood of ſouls, which will be a great weight in the day of God's account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj</hi> But if it be further ſaid, <hi>How then? how muſt we do (there is ſo many wayes) that people might be brought to one way to ſerve God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Do what God requireth of you, and no more, and then we ſhall never ſuffer by you, nor under you; <hi>Do juſtly, love mercy, and walk humbly with your God, this is better than the fat of Rams:</hi> 'tis better than all the outward ſounds and ceremonies, and bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe, while the heart is far from the Lord. And if you judge you are in the right, and your way is right, come forth then with ſpiritual Weapons, mighty ones, in the power of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, and let us ſee you ſhine forth in his Image; let this be your covering, your white Robes, even the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which is the righteouſneſs of the Saints, and lets ſee your meekneſs, patience, gentleneſs, and good example your readineſs by word and deed to convince gain-ſayers in the power and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt; your love to Enemies, your ſelf-denial, your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus; Oh this would reach our hearts, then God's Witneſs would anſwer to you, and this would anſwer the good part in all; and this is the way to bring people to be of one mind in the truth; this is God's way, this is the way the Saints walked in; this is the way we love and deſire; and this alſo would be of good report amongſt all good people; but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54550:7"/>force and compulſion, with a haſty, froward, proud, envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirit, with Staff and Club, and carnal Weapons, and Stocks, and priſoning of people, againſt whom there is no occaſion, but concerning the Law of their God, and matters which are really of Conſcience to God-wards; We ſay, this will never be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lord, nor effect the end neither; nor be of good report amongſt ſober people, nor anſwer the good part in people: And moreover, the Lord God of Life will turn his hand and power againſt them, that ſo turn their hand and power againſt his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for obeying him, and exerciſing their Conſciences towards him, in waiting upon him, and worſhipping him according to that which he hath made manifeſt to them; and ſuch will be more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable for perſecuting now, than the <hi>Jews</hi> were in former dayes; for then the Saints met together, and profeſſed the Name of Jeſus, which the <hi>Jews</hi> did not ſay they believed in. Beſides, it was in appearance ſuch a new way, and ſo different to the Law and manner of Worſhip which the <hi>Jews</hi> had, that they had ſome ſeeming colour in their way; but now for they that profeſſe the Name of Chriſt, and the Scriptures of the New-Teſtament, and the Saints practiſe, and Chriſt's commands to be obeyed, for theſe (all things conſidered) to perſecute people for owning the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt, and for practiſing the ſame things (which they cannot but read) the Saints practiſed, and to hall people, and commit them to Priſon for meeting in the Name of Jeſus, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God and to wait upon him; yea, and to be ſo far from che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing ſuch, as to act the very parts of them that made havock of the Church, and halled out both men and women, and was exceedingly mad, and cauſed ſome to blaſpheme, and committed to Priſon for the ſame things; it doth appear to be great evil, and to be even ſin againſt knowledge, againſt their own Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Chriſtians, and cannot be parallel'd with any of the Saints, but with the Perſecutors, who hated and evilly entreated the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord in former ages, who never could accompliſh their end, though they cauſed many to ſuffer; and now to put all out of doubt, and to give all who oppoſeth the people of God in the way of God, an abſolute anſwer, that they ſhall not be able to accompliſh their end, and therefore it vvould be far better to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54550:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>be quiet, and to mind the Royal Law of Chriſt, leſt they by act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary, do bring innocent ſuffering, and blood upon their own heads, and incur God's heavyſtroke of diſpleaſure againſt them, yea and a fire be kindled in their own bowels, and a worm which ſhall not dye, and a dart ſtrike through the heart and liver, and ſo the end be as bitter as Wormwood, and as ſharp as a two-edged Sword; theſe are Inſtruments of War which the Lord hath in his Quiver, which is reſerved for the day of Battle, when God pleads with all fleſh by fire, and by his ſword, when the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many, when he will rain ſnares upon the wicked, fire and brimſtone, and grievous tempeſts; this is the portion of their Cup: But indeed we do deſire the converſion and ſalvation even of our perſecutors; and therefore to put all out of doubt, as is before ſaid, that there is no prevailing againſt the Lord nor againſt the <hi>Sion</hi> of the Holy One, in whom the Lord is: We ſay, the living God of Heaven and Earth hath made manifeſt unto us the Way to Life, and called us to walk in it, and united our hearts together, (as many as lives in his Power) to ſerve him, and to wait upon him, and to meet together to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in ſpirit and truth; and we are perſwaded to obey the Lord, and believe in the Lord, that he will ſtrengthen us in his Way and Will unto the end: For our ſtrength is in the Lord (and not of our ſelves) who hath called us to follow him through good report and bad report, and not to deny his Way becauſe of ſufferings, but to endure in patience, and let the Lord plead our cauſe in the hearts of his Enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> And if any ſay, <hi>Why will you not ſwear? And why will you meet, ſeeing there is a Law againſt you</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For theſe two things, we ſay, We dare not diſobey the Lord for fear of puniſhment or ſuffering outwardly; and we meet together in the Name and fear of the Lord,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Lord God of Life requireth it of us, that we ſhould meet in his Name and Power, and wait upon him, and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie one another in his love and life, and in our meetings waiting upon the Lord, we have the Preſence of the living God of Life with us, and the feeling of the virtue of his love in our hearts; and he lifts up his countenance upon us, yea and comforteth us by his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54550:8"/>free Spirit, whereby we know and are aſſured, that it is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the mind and will of the Lord, and that he ſpeaks peace unto us: And this being the real truth, let all the honeſt-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed judge how we can in Conſcience leave that which God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of us, in obedience to which we have God's preſence with us, and do that which man requireth of us, contrary to the truth, in obſerving of which we ſhould fall into condemnation, and feel God's anger, and the Teſtimony of his Spirit againſt us, to judge us, which would be greater ſufferings in the inward man, than all the outward ſufferings which we may meet with; for in theſe being faithful, the Lord comforteth our hearts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again, We meet together to wait upon the Lord, becauſe we fear the Lord God, he hath placed his fear in our hearts, and and we know him to be great and mighty, a great King above all Kings, and a great God above all Gods, that is able to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will in Heaven and in Earth, and in the Kingdomes of men, and we know he is worthy to be worſhipped, and to have the heart given up unto him, for he hath power to change the heart, (which men by all their force cannot do) and to give true and laſting peace, which the World can never take away; and his fear being in our hearts, we account him Lord and Ruler in our Conſciences, and worthy to be obeyed in heart, ſoul and ſpirit: And becauſe we fear him more than man, we are bound in duty to obey him, for he hath power over both ſoul and body, which man hath not; for man can but kill the body, he hath not power to kill the ſoul, neither hath he power to redeem the ſoul; neither can man convert the ſoul by any force or penalty outwardly; therefore man doth but labour in vain, for he can neither kil nor cure the ſoul; but the Lord whom we fear, hath power, and is able to kill, and to make alive: And becauſe vve fear him more than man, therefore we chuſe to obey him rather than man, &amp; to meet in God's fear. And this being our condition, let the ſober-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed judge, Hovv can vve deny the Lord vvho hath all Povver, and hath quickned us, &amp; redeemed our ſouls from death, &amp; go to obey man contrary to Chriſt's Doctrine) vvho hath no povver over the Soul. Surely as vve ſtand in God's fear and counſel, vve may not do this evil, and ſin againſt our God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54550:9"/> 3. Again, We meet together to wait upon the Lord, becauſe God hath made it manifeſt to us, and perſwaded us, that the Way in which we walk, is according to his mind and will, and we look not for direction in our Religion, by mans Wiſdom or Will, how we ſhould ſerve and worſhip God; for we know it's God alone by his Spirit, that leads people in the exerciſe of the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it is written; <hi>I the Lord teacheth thee to profit, and leadeth thee in the way in which thou ſhouldeſt go;</hi> and ſo we are content with our Religion which the Lord hath led us into, and in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it we have God's bleſſing, filling our hearts vvith love and joy, peace and ſatisfaction, in which our ſouls are comforted, and vve look not for another Religion contrary to that which vve are in; but our hearts are fixed, vvaiting upon the Lord, and we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it from the Lord, and not upon any ſuch terms, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in it till man made a Law againſt it, or ſpake againſt it, and no longer; but even as the Way of Truth vvas made manifeſt to us, ſo to preſs on in it unto the end: And vve ſee the Wayes and Religions of men to be ſo changeable, ſometimes one vvay, and ſometimes another, that it appears to us, as if men received their Religion but till Orders of another ſort of men to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: And vve ſee many people ſo ready to part vvith their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and take up another, that gives us juſt ground to believe they found not the Preſence of God vvith them in their Way and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe: And ſo it's but looſe vvith them, and they can leave it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion, rather than ſuffer the loſs of any thing for it; and this makes us prize that vvhich God hath made manifeſt to us, the more becauſe vve receive Refreſhment from the Lord, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of our Religion, beſides if vve had been voyd of the true Religion till this day, vve ſhould have been as unſtable as others, toſſed about vvith vvinds of doctrine, and have knovvn, no true reſt to our Souls; but it is vvell knovvn that vve vvere of the ſame mind, that vve are novv, in the time of the former Povvers, and vve received not our Religion from them neither, but from the Lord our God, neither vvas our Religion or vve in the exerciſe of it, confirmed by any Lavv or Decree of theirs, but on the contrary did ſuffer much hardſhip under them, and by them,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54550:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>whom they cheriſhed at that time in the Religion which they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and they then ſaid, <hi>theirs was the right way, and they ſtockt and priſoned many who were contrary to them; and now others ſay they are in the way, and uſeth force and ſuch like to them that differ from them. One ſaid the Law is on our ſide, and we are in the right; the others ſay, The Law is on our ſide, and we are in the right, and you muſt conform, or ſuffer deeply.</hi> We ſay, None of theſe things can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our Conſciences; but come forth in the Power of the Lord, as good examples, with ſpiritual Weapons, if you will perſwade us; for we cannot with a ſafe Conſcience leave our Religion which the Lord hath led us into by his own power, upon theſe things, but muſt rather give up to ſuffer in the Will of the Lord; for we know plainly, it is God alone by his power, that doth bring people into the true Worſhip: And this is according to the Scriptures of Truth, and alſo to the Service which is now allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for 'tis ſaid in the Collect for that which is called the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Sunday after Trinity, <hi>Almighty and moſt merciful God, of whoſe onely gift it cometh that thy faithful people do unto thee true and laudible ſervice:</hi> Now then, if it come onely by the gift of God that the faithful do true ſervice unto God, then they that would force people from ſerving God according to his gift given them, would force them from the true and laudable ſervice of God, and to make them act contrary to the gift of God, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably lead and force people from the true Worſhip of God, into hypocriſie, and a falſe, feigned, lifeleſs and heartleſs Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, in which the Lord takes no pleaſure. And ſo this being truly conſidered, we can put it to the Conſciences of all that fear the Lord, to judge whether we can with a ſafe Conſcience leave our Religion which God hath led us into, and the exerciſe of it, according to the gift of God, by which onely true ſervice is done to God, in which alſo we find acceptance with God through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and go to a Religion in the will of man, contrary to the gift of God, by force and compulſion, where we could not act affectionately with our hearts, nor yet find the bleſſing and preſence of God with us, acting contrary to the gift of God: Truly it is in our hearts and conſciences, as the truth of the Lord, that we may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>affly do it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54550:10"/>
            <p> But if any ſhould object and ſay, <hi>Your Religion is but new, or of a late ſtanding, ours is a hundred years old, or thereabouts, ſince Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery was brought from having the upper hand in this Nation; for they forced, but they were out of the way; but ours is a reformed Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis anſwered, That though the name or denomination by which we are diſtinguiſhed from other people, be but of late years, which was caſt upon us by ſome that mocked us, becauſe of the Power of the Lord, which cauſed many to quake and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; yet the Life in which we live, and the truth which we profeſs, is ancient, and the practice in which we are exerciſed in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, is according to the truth and practiſe of the Saints of old: And ſo it might be ſaid of the Saints, and of <hi>Paul</hi> when he was converted, and turned from the <hi>Jews</hi> Worſhip, that it was a new Religion; but it was the mighty Power of God that chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them, though many in that day oppoſed them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſo we ſay, Force now, with Priſons and carnal Weapons is of the ſame nature as it was formerly, in the Papiſts and others; for they ſaid they had a Law, and they were the true Church, and they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced about Religion, and killed many; and now here is but the ſame Argument, The Law ſaith ſo and ſo: Therefore we ſee the ſame Nature forcing now, as formerly, as it's ſaid, <hi>He that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit;</hi> even ſo it is now.</p>
            <p>And for being of a hundred years ſtanding, this adds no ſtrength to it at all, for the <hi>Jews</hi> Religion was far more ancient, and yet being in the perſecuting nature, and reſiſting the Holy One and the Juſt, though they profeſſed God with their mouth, yet that would not cover them, nor will it cover people now, to profeſs God with their mouth, while they are found in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſteps and practiſe, of them who perſecuted the Saints and Servants of God in ages paſt.</p>
            <p>And for that which is ſaid, That we are but of late years; We ſay, Men are not true Chriſtians by Generation, neither by an outward Profeſſion, but by an inward change in the heart, wrought by the Power of God in the Regeneration. And ſo if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54550:10"/>it be but a few years in compariſon, ſince we, or any of us were changed and turned to the Lord, yet it was in the time when the Lord was pleaſed, and ſaw good to viſit us; and we can truly ſay it was an acceptable day and time when we were turned from darkneſs to the true Light and from the Power of Satan to God: And we are glad of it, and can ſay, Bleſſed be the Lord for it if it had been but yeſterday, that any of us were renewed in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of our minds to God; for it is matter of joy to us, that the Lord hath gathered us in our day and time, from off the barren Mountains, into his Fold, to wait upon him, and to receive teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſatisfaction from him: This is far more to us to know the Lord changing us in our day, and bringing us to know the things that pertaineth to our everlaſting peace, than to have a large Profeſſion of the Saints words, and yet to be out of the Saints Life, and out of the way where true peace and reſt is found to the ſoul; and ſo the Lord having manifeſted his Truth to us, and brought us into the Religion in which he manifeſts his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to us, we are content to wait in the Will of the Lord, and may not forſake our Religion, nor the aſſembling of our ſelves together, becauſe man ſaith to the contrary, but walk according to the gift of God, by which onely it is, that true and faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is performed unto him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Again, we meet together to wait upon the Lord, that our Conſciences may be kept clear towards him, that we may have the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God, which if we ſhould walk contrary to that which the Lord hath made manifeſt, here would be ſhipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience; for ſo it was formerly, if any forſook the Lord and his Truth after they had taſted of his good Word, if they fell away from that which they had once known and profeſſed of the Truth and Goſpel of Jeſus, they made ſhipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience, and then they could not have the anſwer of a good Conſcience, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had they peace with God; and what remained if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo, but a certain fearful looking for of Judgement and fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry indignation, which will devour. And therefore we knowing the preciouſneſs of the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God, do prize it, and eſteem it as a Jewel of great worth, and we
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54550:11"/>may not forſake the way of the Lord, wherein we have the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of a good Conſcience (becauſe of outward force) &amp; go into that in which we ſhould ſuffer anguiſh, &amp; have a certain fearful looking for of judgment, and a ſting in our own conſciences; therefore we can put it to all who fear the Lord to judg of, if it be not ſafe for us to abide in the way of the Lord, and to be faithful to him, though we may meet with ſufferings in this world.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Again, we meet together in the fear of the Lord, and own the doctrine of Chriſt to live in it, becauſe we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in the fear and power of the Lord God of life; who is our ſtrength, that nothing ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which we have in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> our Lord; the love of God is ſo comfortable, and his favour is ſo refreſhing to us, and the teſtimonie of his ſpirit is ſo ſatisfactorie in our hearts, that we are perſwaded, nothing will be able to ſeparte us; our ſtrength is in the Lord, and he is all-ſufficient to keep us through all, by his mighty power; unto the end waiting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and abiding in his power, he is able to ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt; and this were the Saints formerly perſwaded off, that nothing ſhould be able to ſeparate them from the love of God, &amp; they met with many hardſhips &amp; were oftentimes cruelly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, &amp; ſhamefully handled as the <hi>Scriptures</hi> declare; yet through all the Lord was with his people, and comforted their hearts in their following of him, and the love of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded to them and in them, and they were Conquerors through him that loved them. Now if any at that time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the truth for fear of man, or any other thing, they came to ſuffer in there hearts, and to feel ſorrow in their inward man; for when iniquity enters into the heart, it darkens the underſtanding, and alſo the creature loſeth the ſence of the love of God; and if there be not repentance, and a returning unto the Lord, Iniquity grows more ſtrong, and love grows cold in ſuch, and the heart grows worſe and worſe, and is hardned by degrees againſt the Lord and his people, and then there is a ſeparation from the love of God, &amp; the feeling, and earneſt of ſorrow and tribulation upon every one that doth evill; therefore we are perſwaded that it is ſafe for us to wait
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54550:11"/>upon the Lord in the way which he hath made manifeſt unto us, that ſo we may receive the power to renew our ſtrength, that we may walk on in the path of life, and nothing ſeparate us from the love of God which we have in Chriſt Jeſus. Shall tribulation, or affliction, or principalities, or powers ſeparate us from the love of God? Shall force by carnal weapons, or Priſons cauſe us to deny that which God hath made manifeſt unto us? Is there Powers againſt us, Thrones againſt us? well, this is ſafe for us, to abide in the counſel of God, that we may always feel his love in our hearts; and if we ſuffer, let us ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer here, becauſe of our faithfulneſs to the Lord: If we muſt go to Priſon, let us ſtand in the power of God, that his love, and life, bleſſing, and heavenly preſence may be with us: Better to ſuffer outwardly in priſons, and holes, &amp; have the love and preſence of the Lord with us, then to diſobey the Lord, and walk contrary to his gift, and ſo ſuffer inward anguiſh and ſorrow of heart, and ſomething ſeparate us from the love of God, and then who can ſpeak peace to us, if the Lord ſpeak trouble; but if the Lord ſpeak peace, it's no matter though man may ſpeak trouble; though the wrath of man may riſe high, yet he that doth whatſoever he will in heaven and in earth, he on make it to turn to his praiſe, and the reſt of it he will reſtrain; and bleſſed are they that have the Lord with them, on their ſide; he ſpeaks peace to them in the midſt of all, his love refreſheth our hearts, and ſo to put all out of doubt, we are perſwaded in the power of the Lord, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will be able to ſeparate us from the love which we have in our Saviour; and here it is good to a bide, and not to give one foot back, to give any ground unto the enemy, but to continue where the love of God is with us, and his bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with us, comforting our hearts, which people doth not find with them in diſobedience, walking and acting contrary to what the Lord hath made manifeſt to them; and ſo we can put it to the Conſciences of all people who have any ſence of the love of God in their hearts, Whether it can be ſafe for us to forſake the Way of peace and reſt which God hath made manifeſt unto us, and in which we have the Love of God with us, and to go into a Way by force, into which the Spirit of the Lord doth not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54550:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>lead us, where we ſhall find anguiſh and ſorrow, and ſomething ſeparating us from the Love of God, and where God would not ſpeak peace to us, but trouble; ſurely we are perſwaded to abide in that which the Lord hath made manifeſt to us, and our faith is in the power of God, that nothing will be able to ſeparate us from the love of God.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Again, we are perſwaded to continue in the Way of Truth, meeting together in the fear of the Lord, to ſerve him, becauſe we find the Lord requireth of us to bear a faithful Teſtimony, and witneſs to his Name and Truth, which he hath made known to us at this day; and though man require the contrary, and would force us to yeild, yet we may not deny the Lord and his Truth, but muſt bear witneſs to his Name in obedience to his Will; for we are not our own, but the Lords; neither muſt vve ſerve our ſelves, nor do our ovvn Will, nor the Wills of others, vvhoſe Will is not according to the Will of God; but we muſt ſerve the Lord, and be faithful to him; and vve ſee vve cannot ſerve tvvo Maſters, nor cannot be partakers of the love of God, if vve be in the love of the World, and follovv after the luſts of it; and if vve love any thing more than Chriſt, vve ſhould not be true Diſciples and followers of him.</p>
            <p>And if it be objected, <hi>Why cannot you do as men would have you? What, God knows your hearts, and you may keep your hearts to your ſelves, and conform outwardly for all that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's anſvvered, Nay, vve cannot, becauſe God requireth it of us, to bear vvitneſs to his Name and Truth; and vve may not deal doubly or deceitfully in ſhevving that before men, vvhich vve are not in our hearts to God for the people that God hath form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to himſelf, muſt ſhevv forth his praiſe. And though it be true, that God knows the heart of every one, yet he looks for fruit alſo to be brought forth, that hee may be glorified. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Scriptures, that there vvere many occaſions ſought againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> but they could find none againſt him, except it vvere concerning the Lavv of his God; and they that hated him, conſulted to get a Decree, that none ſhould ask any Petition of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54550:12"/>God or man for thirty dayes, ſave of the King; if he did, he vvas to be caſt into the Den of Lyons: and the Decree vvas ſealed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lavv of the <hi>Meades</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi> Novv it cannot be denied but <hi>Daniel</hi> might have prayed to God in his heart, and his evil-vviſhers have knovvn little of it; but he vvas taught by the Lord to pray openly, and to confeſs unto him, that he vvas great, mighty and povverful. And ſo though the Decree vvas ſealed, he (as if he regarded it not) went and prayed to his God three times a day upon his knees, vvith his Windovv open, and his face tovvards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſo held forth his Teſtimony, and bore vvitneſs to the Lord, that he vvas vvorthy to be ſought unto, and that he vvas not to be limited (by an outvvard Decree, though a ſtrong one) from praying and calling upon the Name of the Lord, and the Lord vvas vvith him; and though he ſuffered the adventure of being caſt into the Lyons Den, yet the God of Heaven vvas his Preſerver, and he held forth a precious Teſtimony, and God vvas much glorified; for it was ſaid, yea and proclaimed through many Nations, that all ſhould fear and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the God of <hi>Daniel,</hi> for there was no other God that could ſave in ſuch ſort.</p>
            <p>And alſo the three Children that vvould not bovv, though the King had commanded it, that vvhen the voice of the Muſick was heard, all ſhould bow to the Image which he had ſet up; yet they vvould not obey, for it vvas contrary to the Lavv of their God, and great Wrath vvas againſt them, and the Fornace vvas very hot, yet the Lord ſaved them, and they bore a precious Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Lord in obedience to his Law, and the Lord was much glorified, and vvas proclaimed through many Nations to be the onely and true God, and the King himſelf did praiſe and honor, and extol the God of Heaven, all whoſe Works are Truth, and his Wayes Judgement, and thoſe vvho vvalk in pride, he is able to a baſe.</p>
            <p>But now if any ſhould ſay, <hi>Theſe were Heathen Kings, and ſo not to be obeyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54550:13"/>
            <p> It's anſwered, They are more excuſable therefore, than thoſe that in words profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, and Scriptures, and the Saints practiſe, and yet are found perſecuting thoſe who live in the Power of the Lord, and forcing by pains and penalties, not according to, but quite contrary to the practiſe of the Saints, whoſe Words they profeſs, and are found in the very ſteps of them who perſecuted the Saints and Servants of God, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teſtifie; and are ſo far from the Doctrine of Chriſt, as to forgive treſpaſſes, and to do as they would be done unto, and to love enemies, and to pray for them that perſecute them, that they do abſolutely treſpaſs againſt them who give them no juſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and do to others as they would not be done unto, were it their caſe, (and let God's Witneſs judge) and doth even hate and cruelly handle their Friends, who wiſh them well from their hearts, and perſecute them who pray for them. And ſurely, for theſe things will the Lord viſit, and in the mean time we find that the Lord requireth it of us, to be faithful to him in what he hath made manifeſt unto us, that we may bear a true Teſtimony, and faithful Witneſs to the truth, and for the Lord, that he may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie himſelf by us; for we are not our own, but his, who hath formed us, and called us to follow him.</p>
            <p>And therefore let the wiſe in heart-judge; Can it be ſafe for us to loſe our Teſtimony, and to ceaſe following the Lord, and living in that which he hath made known unto us to be his mind and wil concerning us, in which we have the Arm and Power of the Lord with us, and him to take our parts, and to go to that which he hath not called us unto, where vve could bear no Teſtimony for him, (for he that goes from the Truth which God hath made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, loſeth his Teſtimony) where fruits would be brought forth unto death, and not unto life, and the hand of the Lord wil turn againſt ſuch; for them that honor the Lord, he will honor; but they that ſlight his Counſel, and deſpiſe his Will, ſhall be light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed; all which duly conſidered, we cannot (as we live to God) but bear witneſs to his Name, and hold forth that Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which the Lord hath committed unto us.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Again, We are given up to obey and ſerve the Lord accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which he hath made known unto us, becauſe no man
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54550:13"/>muſt give an account unto God for us, or anſwer for us in his day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be manifeſt, and he wil reward every one according to their deeds: But we muſt ſtand before the Judgement-Seat of Chriſt; to receive a portion from him, and not others for us: Therefore we may not deny the Lord becauſe of Force, Pains, Priſons or Penalties, becauſe they that ſo force us, will not anſwer for us, though weight enough may be upon themſelves; yet that would not free us if we ſhould forſake the Way of the Lord made known to us: And let all people in ſoberneſs judge what reaſon there is that others ſhould force us from that which we believe, to that which they believe, and yet if we periſh by that means, they can neither help us, nor anſwer for us: Is it not therefore meet, that we ſhould live in that Way in which we dare dye, and give up all unto the Lord in, and not be forc'd out of that Way in which vve have peace and love, and the preſence of the Lord vvith us, into a vvay vvhere pain and anguiſh would fill our hearts, and leanneſs and emptineſs vvould be upon our ſouls; and yet they that forced us from our good Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and ſafe Harbour, where we lay at Anchor ſafe from the ſtorm, would neither bring us to any ſure reſting place, nor yet preſerve us from the Winds and Storms, and terrible Tempeſts; but we muſt by reaſon of ſuch a force, unavoidably ſuffer ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack: We ſay, We may call Heaven and Earth, yea Angels and all juſt men, to bear witneſs to our Cauſe; yea, and the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God of Life, in whoſe hand is the breath of all living, to judge between us and our perſecutors in this matter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="queries">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54550:14"/>
            <head>Some Queries to any that profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtians, and yet are Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of them who at this day are ſufferers for Conſcience-ſake.</head>
            <div n="1" type="query">
               <head>
                  <hi>QUERY</hi> I.</head>
               <p>VVHether is it well done, or evil, for them that profeſs themſelves Chriſtian Magiſtrates, to caſt into Priſon people who are Chriſtians; who have God's Power and Life with them, and in them, that judgeth the Wicked, and turneth the Heathen to the knowledge of God?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="query">
               <head>QUERY II.</head>
               <p>Whether any do come to the knowledge of God till they be turned to Chriſt the true Light that ſhineth in the hearts of true Chriſtians, in which they have God's Power and Life with them, and in them, which they dare not ſinne againſt, though they ſuffer?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="query">
               <head>QUERY III.</head>
               <p>And whether they are not ſuch Chriſtians that ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for keeping the Commands of Chriſt, and do abide in his Doctrine, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="query">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:54550:14"/>
               <head>QUERY IV.</head>
               <p>Whether is it not better for Chriſtians to obey Chriſt, than man, whoſe Commands are contrary to Chriſt's Commands? Judge and anſwer as in God's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, in which all muſt give an account to God in the laſt day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="query">
               <head>QUERY V.</head>
               <p>Whether did <hi>Daniel</hi> well, or did he evil, in petitioning and praying to his God, when <hi>Darius</hi> the King had ſigned the Decree, That whoſoever ſhould ask any Petition (<hi>Dan.</hi> 6, 7.) of God or man for thirty dayes, ſave of the King, ſhould be caſt into the Den of Lyons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="query">
               <head>QUERY VI.</head>
               <p>Alſo, did the three Children well, or did they evil, in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering their bodies to be caſt into the hot fiery Fornace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.20. becauſe they could not actually obey the King's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, becauſe is was contrary to the Command of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="query">
               <head>QUERY VII.</head>
               <p>And further, Was it evil in <hi>Mordeoai,</hi> or was it good that he kept the Law of his God, contrary to the King's Law, (<hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.2.) in going to the King's Gate in Sackcloath, when evil was intended againſt God's people, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="query">
               <head>QUERY VIII.</head>
               <p>Did the Apoſtles well, or did they evil (who were Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) in obeying the Commands of Chriſt, before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of men, eſpecially when the Commands of men were contrary to the Commands of Chriſt? Judge, and let the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54550:15"/>Truth anſwer, and whether it is well or evil in Chriſtians to do ſo now, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="query">
               <head>QUERY IX.</head>
               <p>If it be ſaid, Theſe were Heathen Kings that thus perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted God's people, we query, Whether they that profeſs chemſelves Chriſtian Magiſtrates, be not more inexcuſable in the day of Chriſt, in living contrary unto more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, who perſecutes the followers of Chriſt in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, than the Heathen Rulers were in the times of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? Read and conſider.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="query">
               <head>QUERY X.</head>
               <p>Whether Chriſt's followers now in righteouſneſs meeting together in Chriſt's Name, and in his Spirit to worſhip God, be in the well-doing, or in the evil? Let Truth ſpeak, that God may be glorified.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="query">
               <head>QUERY XI.</head>
               <p>And if ſuch Worſhippers together in Chriſt's Name and Spirit, be in the well-doing, Whether they ought not by Chriſtian-Magiſtrates (who have the Power) to be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in outward peace from the violence of the Wicked, who are filled vvith envy againſt the righteous, as they vvere in all ages, and from the hands of the Heathen that combineth together to do vvickedly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="query">
               <head>QUERY XII.</head>
               <p>If the Church be in God, (2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.1.) and God be in all places, and the Church be the Houſhold of Faith, then we query, If the Church be met together in ſome place, whether it be not according to the practice of the primitive Saints, and according to the New-Teſtament, and the tenor of the holy Scriptures, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="query">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54550:15"/>
               <head>QUERY XIII.</head>
               <p>And was it lawful for Chriſtians to meet together in an upper Room in the Apoſtles days, (as in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.13. and <hi>Acts</hi> 20 8.) and is it not lawful for Chriſtians to meet together ſo novv? Or is there any Law of Chriſt to the contrary? And are they not his Laws that Chriſtians ought to mind and keep concerning the Worſhip of God, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="query">
               <head>QUERY XIV.</head>
               <p>Whether Chriſtians as concerning their Worſhip to God in Chriſt Jeſus, ought not to hear Chriſt alone, whom all ought to hear, and receive his Counſel in their Conſciences? And whether it is not his right to rule in the Conſciences of Chriſtians in the Worſhip of God, and in things appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="query">
               <head>QUERY XV.</head>
               <p>Whether any thing ought to be impoſed by Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates on the Conſciences of any true Chriſtians now, as concerning their meeting together in the true Worſhip of God, or commanding them to ſwear, or they muſt ſuffer, as it appertaineth to Conſcience; or is it Chriſt's right there to command? Or whether ſwearing or fearing to ſwear, be not, or ought not to be matter of Conſcience to all, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="query">
               <head>QUERY XVI.</head>
               <p>Whether Chriſtian Magiſtrates impoſing ſwearing on Chriſtians Conſciences, or any other thing contrary to Chriſt's perſwaſions in the conſcience, and contrary to the holy Scriptures, be right in the ſight of God, or will ſtand approved in the day of account, yea or nay?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="query">
               <head>QUERY XVII.</head>
               <p>Or whether is it right for Chriſtian Magiſtrates to impoſe any thing on Chriſtians conſciences, before they convince them that the things impoſed are lawful to them in the ſight of God, yea or nay? Read with patience, and conſider.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="query">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:54550:16"/>
               <head>QUERY XVIII.</head>
               <p>And if this be denied by Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and they do not convince Chriſtians of the lawfulneſs to God of the things they do impoſe, which may cauſe great ſufferings to the righteous; Whether it may not incur the anger of God alſo againſt themſelves, and cauſe God to impoſe that upon them, which may be greater ſuffering in their inward man, than all the outward ſufferings of the innocent in this time, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>Conſider theſe things in the fear of God, and let Truth anſwer.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Wilkinſon.</signed>
               </closer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, Ye have not obeyed me in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming freedom every man to his Brother, and every man to his Neighbour: Behold, I proclaim a liberty for you, ſaith the Lord, to the Sword, to the Peſtilence, and to the Famine; and I will make you a terror to all the Kingdoms of the Earth,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Jer. 34.17.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
